A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Communications, Advisor on Communications, Office Files of Fred W. Friendly FA616
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Communications, Advisor on Communications, Office Files of Fred W. Friendly
1946-1980
1966-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Friendly, Fred W.
Ford Foundation
FA616
25.2 Cubic Feet 21 record cartons
Biographical / Historical
Fred W. Friendly was born Ferdinand Friendly Wachenheimer in New York City on October 30, 1915, and was raised in Providence, Rhode Island. He attended Nichols Junior College. Friendly's professional career began in 1938 in Providence, where he wrote, produced and narrated dramatized biographies for a local radio station. From 1941-1945, Friendly served in the U.S. Army Information and Education Section as a lecturer and correspondent at domestic military bases, in southeast Asia and in Europe.
In 1947, while working as a news producer for the National Broadcasting Company (NBC), Friendly met Edward R. Murrow and began a professional association and friendship that endured until Murrow's death in 1965. They produced audio documentary recordings on 20th century world history under the title I Can Hear It Now. Beginning in 1951, when Friendly joined the Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS), they collaborated on the See It Now television program, and later worked together on CBS Reports. Milestones of their years together was a 1954 See It Now broadcast that cast a critical eye on the anti-Communist crusade of Senator Joe McCarthy, and a 1960 CBS Reports investigation of conditions faced by migrant farm workers titled "Harvest of Shame."
Friendly was named President of the CBS News Division in 1964. Under his leadership the network broadcast Town Meeting of the World, which brought world leaders together via live satellite transmission to discuss world affairs, and Vietnam Perspective, a program devoted to discussion of the Vietnam War and its impact on the American people. For his work at CBS Friendly received numerous George Foster Peabody Awards. Friendly resigned from CBS in February 1966 in a dispute over the network's decision to broadcast situation comedy reruns instead of hearings on the Vietnam War then being conducted by the U.S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
Friendly joined the staff of the Ford Foundation as Advisor on Television in March 1966. In this position he worked closely with Foundation President McGeorge Bundy to define and implement a grant making agenda focused on sustained support for public television stations and networks and for policy institutions that represented the public interest on significant telecommunications issues. Within six months of his appointment, Friendly made a major impact on the communications landscape when he and Bundy submitted a statement to the Federal Communications Commission that proposed the creation of a non-profit owned satellite system that would finance public television with income generated through fees charged to commercial networks for carrying their transmissions. The plan never came to fruition, but it influenced political debate over public television financing. Other significant achievements of Friendly's tenure at the Foundation included:
• Creation of the Public Broadcast Laboratory, which produced live programs for a national network of educational television stations from 1967-1969 • Supporting the establishment of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, the Public Broadcasting Service, and National Educational Television • Founding of the Cable Television Information Center to advise communities on franchising, regulation, and public-service applications of cable television • Supporting a program of educational fellowships for minority journalists • Creation of the Media and Law seminars, which convened jurists and journalists to discuss hypothetical court cases that highlighted areas of conflict between the press and the courts
During the mid and late 1970s, Friendly oversaw a substantial withdrawal of Foundation support for public television programming and infrastructure development as those costs were increasingly met by government funding, viewer support and corporate sponsorship. In 1975 Friendly's job title was changed to Advisor on Communications, to reflect a shift in the emphasis of his work which was increasingly focused on media policy, journalism and law. Significant projects in these areas included support to the Aspen Institute Program on Communications and Society, and funding for research and conferences on the impact of television on children.
Friendly retired from the Ford Foundation in 1980.
Concurrent with his career at the Ford Foundation, Friendly was Edward R. Murrow Professor of Journalism at Columbia University. He was the author of several books, including Due To Circumstances Beyond Our Control (1967), an account of his CBS career and an analysis of commercial and non-commercial television, and The Good Guys, the Bad Guys and the First Amendment: Free Speech vs. Fairness in Broadcasting (1975).
Fred W. Friendly died on March 3, 1998.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation first made grants in the field of media and communications in 1951, when funds were provided to the Radio and Television Workshop for the production of broadcast programming. Through 1977, the foundation gave over $295 million to develop public television stations, networks and content. Fred W. Friendly was hired as Advisor on Television in 1966, and later headed the Foundation's Office on Television, which coordinated grants in this field beginning in 1968. Friendly oversaw an expansion of grant making into such related fields as telecommunications and telecommunications policy, journalism education and media law. In February 1975 the Office of Public Broadcasting was renamed the Office of Communications and Friendly's title was changed to Advisor on Communications, reflecting a shift in the emphasis of the program. The Foundation dramatically scaled back funding for public television development and programming, and increasingly focused its resources on the public policy, research and media law elements of the portfolio. Some funding continued to go to public TV programming on subjects related to the interests of other parts of the Foundation, such as public affairs and the arts. Shortly after Friendly's retirement in 1980, the Office of Communications was disbanded as a separate unit of the Foundation, with ongoing grants related to communications being channeled through other program divisions.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Fred W. Friendly, Ford Foundation Advisor on Television (1966-1975) and Advisor on Communications (1975-1980) document his oversight of program development and grants in the fields of public television, telecommunications and media law. The collection spans 1945-1980 and consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, grant proposals, writings, speeches, news clippings and photographs.
The Office Files of Fred W. Friendly document the professional activities of the noted journalist, educator and grant maker during the period 1945-1980, with an emphasis on the years of his association with the Ford Foundation, 1966-1980. The bulk of the records concern Friendly's work as the Foundation's Advisor on Television and Advisor on Communications, and consist of correspondence, memos and reports pertaining to Foundation grant making to support public television development and programming, telecommunications policy research, journalism education and media law. The collection also documents Friendly's pre-Ford Foundation career as a television producer and executive at CBS, his activities as a Professor of Journalism at Columbia University, and his personal life. There are substantial records documenting Friendly's public speaking engagements, his published writings, and his chairmanship of the Mayor's Advisory Task Force on CATV and telecommunications.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. This collection was originally accessioned by the Ford Foundation in 2004. The collection was transferred to, and officially accessioned, by the Rockefeller Archive Center in 2012. Box 14, containing the contents of Series 5, has not been transferred to RAC and is therefore not available for research.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into seven series: Series I: Correspondence; Series II: Mayor's Advisory Task Force on CATV and Telecommunications; Series III: Media and Law Seminars; Series IV: Photographs; Series V: Speeches and Interviews; Series VI: Subjects; Series VII: Writings
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from the papers and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Completion of a use agreement is required prior to providing scholarly access. See RAC Head of Reference (or applicable designee) for details.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Mass Communications; Television; Television broadcasting; Mass media; Radio; Radio broadcasting -- History
- Correspondence, 1945-1980; I; 13.8 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence, 1945-1980 Letters, memoranda, telegrams and supporting documentation relating to Friendly's professional activities and personal life. The correspondence is arranged in three subseries.
  A. Alphabetical, 1955-1980 Correspondence with individuals and organizations concerning Ford Foundation program development, grant making and grantee activities in the fields of public television, telecommunications policy, journalism and media law. While the bulk of the letters are to or from Friendly himself, there are also numerous documents authored by or addressed to other members of his staff including Stuart Sucherman, David Davis and Tinka Nobbe. Of particular interest are letters and reports exchanged with dozens of public television stations across the United States that evaluate their programming, finances and operation, correspondence with NASA and COMSAT regarding satellite communication systems, and information on the merger of New York stations WNET and WNDT that created Channel 13. A few items date from Friendly's years at CBS and relate to his work as a producer and executive in the network's News Division. There are also several items pertaining to Friendly's collaboration with Edward R. Murrow, as well as letters from such prominent individuals as jurists Hugo Black and Warren Berger, political journalist William F. Buckley and television personality Bill Moyers. The subseries also documents the day to day operation of the Office of Public Broadcasting and its successor, the Office of Communications, and includes such routine business correspondence as consultant's reports and general inquiries from grant and job seekers. Files are arranged alphabetically.
  B. Chronological, 1971-1980 Outgoing letters written by Friendly and members of his staff at the Ford Foundation, dealing with grant making and administrative matters, arranged by date of writing. There is some duplication of items filed by author or recipient in the Alphabetical subseries.
  C. Personal, 1945-1979 Letters to and from friends, family, colleagues and associates concerning financial affairs, family matters, school and summer camp arrangements for Friendly's children, his activities as a member of the Board of Trustees of the Riverdale Country School and social engagements. Of particular interest is a May 19, 1945 letter written by Friendly to his mother regarding his visit to the Mauthausen concentration camp shortly after its liberation by the American military (box 12, folder 16).
  - Alphabetical, 1955 - 1980; A
    - A, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 1)
    - Action on Smoking and Health, 1968 - 1969 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 2)
    - Adams, Arlin M., 1978 - 1980 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 3)
    - Adler, Norman, 1966 - 1971 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 4)
    - Adler, Peter, 1968 - 1971 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 5)
    - Alcoa, 1966 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 6)
    - Alicia Patterson Foundation, 1979 - 1980 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 7)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1966 - 1970 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 8)
    - American Broadcasting Company (ABC), 1966 - 1980 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 9)
    - ABC – Good Morning America, 1979 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 10)
    - ABC/International Telephone and Telegraph (ITT) merger, 1967 - 1968 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 11)
    - American Cancer Society, 1967 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 12)
    - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 1969 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 13)
    - American Institute for Political Communication, 1970 - 1971 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 14)
    - American Telephone and Telegraph (AT&T), 1966 - 1969 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 15)
    - Arthur D. Little, Inc., 1969 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 16)
    - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies – General, 1970 - 1979 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 17-20)
    - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies – Program on Communications and Society, 1972 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 21-22)
    - Atlanta Interfaith Broadcasters, 1970 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 23)
    - Atlantic Monthly, 1967 - 1971 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 24)
    - Atwater, Verne S., 1966 - 1967 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 25)
    - Australian Broadcasting Commission, 1967 - 1968 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 26)
    - B, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 27-28)
    - Balk, Alfred, 1971 - 1979 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 29)
    - Barrett, Edward W., 1973 - 1979 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 30)
    - Barrett, Halsey V., 1970 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 31)
    - Bass, Milton R., 1966 - 1969 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 32)
    - Black, Hugo, 1967 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 33)
    - Bliss, Ed, 1969 - 1979 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 34)
    - Books – requests for reviews by Friendly, 1968 - 1971 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 35)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, 1966 - 1967 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 36)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), 1966 - 1979 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 37-38)
    - British Information Services, 1970 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 39)
    - Brooke, Edward W., 1968 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 40)
    - Brookings Institution, 1967 - 1970 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 41)
    - Buckley, William F., 1972 - 1980 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 42)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1966 - 1972 (Box 1 (33249), Folder 43)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1973 - 1979, n.d. (Box 2 (33672), Folder 1)
    - Bundy, McGeorge – retirement, 1979 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 2)
    - Bureau of National Affairs – Media Law Reporter, 1976 - 1977 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 3)
    - Burger, Warren, E., 1967 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 4)
    - Burtin, Cipe, 1966 - 1967 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 5)
    - Businessmen's Educational Fund, 1970 - 1971 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 6)
    - C, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 7-9)
    - Cables and telegrams, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 10-11)
    - Califano, Joseph A., 1976 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 12)
    - California Institute of Technology, 1967 - 1971 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 13)
    - Call for Action, 1971 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 14)
    - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC), 1966 - 1967 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 15)
    - Capital Cities Broadcasting, 1967 - 1968 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 16)
    - Carnegie Commission on the Future of Public Broadcasting, 1977 - 1979 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 17)
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1966 - 1967 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 18)
    - Catledge, Turner, 1970 - 1971 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 19)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, 1966 - 1967 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 20)
    - Century Association, 1978 - 1979 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 21)
    - Children's Television Workshop, 1968 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 22)
    - Clarke, Arthur C., 1967 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 23)
    - Clarkson, Gary, 1965 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 24)
    - Colleges and Universities, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 25)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS) – memoranda, 1955 - 1966 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 26)
    - CBS – miscellaneous (alphabetical), 1950 - 1966 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 27-30)
    - CBS – miscellaneous (chronological), 1966 - 1980 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 31-35)
    - CBS – regarding Friendly's resignation from, 1966 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 36)
    - Columbia University, 1957 - 1962 (Box 2 (33672), Folder 37)
    - Columbia University, 1966 - 1979 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 1-2)
    - Columbia University – First Amendment and Electronic Media Project, 1971 - 1972 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 3)
    - Columbia University School of Journalism students, 1968 - 1971 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 4)
    - Communications Satellite Corporation (COMSAT), 1974 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 5)
    - Community Television of South Florida, 1978 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 6)
    - Computer Television, Inc., 1970 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 7)
    - Congratulations – regarding Friendly's appointments at Ford Foundation and Columbia University, 1966 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 8)
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, 1967 - 1979 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 9-11)
    - Cousins, Norman, 1970 - 1972 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 12)
    - Cowlan, Bert, 1978 - 1979 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 13)
    - Cox, Archibald, 1968 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 14)
    - Culkin, John M., 1965 - 1970 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 15)
    - Cuninggim, Merrimon, 1973 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 16)
    - D, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 17)
    - Dahl, Norman C., 1971 - 1972 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 18)
    - Davis, David M., 1969 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 19-21)
    - Diamond, Edwin, 1966 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 22)
    - Dressner, Howard R., 1966 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 23)
    - Drew, Elizabeth, 1972 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 24)
    - E, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 25)
    - Eastern Educational Network, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 26)
    - Education Development Center, 1970 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 27)
    - Educational Broadcasting Corporation, 1971 - 1978 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 28)
    - Educom, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 29)
    - Elliot, Barbara R., 1966 - 1967 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 30)
    - Evans, Harold, 1974 - 1979 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 31)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 32)
    - F, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 3 (33679), Folder 33)
    - Federal Communications Commission (FCC), 1966 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 1-3)
    - Feldzamen, Alvin N., 1967 - 1968 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 4)
    - Ferry, W.H. (Ping), 1967 - 1970 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 5)
    - Ford, Henry II, 1966 - 1977 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 6)
    - Ford Motor Company, 1968 - 1972 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 7)
    - Fulbright, J.W., 1966 - 1970 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 8)
    - Fund for Documentaries, 1976 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 9)
    - G, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 10)
    - Gannett Newspaper Foundation, 1976 - 1978 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 11)
    - General Learning Corporation, 1968 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 12)
    - Ginsburg, David, 1966 - 1979 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 13)
    - Goldmann, Robert B., 1971 - 1979 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 14)
    - Goldmark, Peter C., 1970 - 1971 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 15)
    - Goodale, James, 1979 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 16)
    - Greene, Hugh, 1970 - 1971 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 17)
    - Grossman, Lawrence K., 1966 - 1979 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 18)
    - Gude, J.G., 1970 - 1977 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 19)
    - H, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 20-21)
    - Hampshire College, 1967 - 1970 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 22)
    - Hanna, Lee, 1970 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 23)
    - Harper's, 1966 - 1969 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 24)
    - Harris, Fred F., 1955 - 1971 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 25-26)
    - Harvard University, 1978 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 27)
    - Harvard University – Niemann Foundation for Journalism, 1974 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 28)
    - Heard, Alexander, 1969 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 29)
    - Henderson, Hazel, 1970 - 1971 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 30)
    - Hitchcock, Ethan A., 1970 - 1977 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 31)
    - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1971 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 32)
    - Howe II, Harold, 1971 - 1979 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 33-34)
    - Hughes Aircraft Company, 1968 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 35)
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1966 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 36)
    - I, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 37)
    - I Can Hear It Now/The Sixties – regarding, 1969 - 1973 (Box 4 (33689), Folder 38)
    - Independent Television Authority, 1971 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 1)
    - Indiana University – The Poynter Center, 1978 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 2)
    - Institute for International Education, 1970 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 3)
    - Institute for Journalism Education, 1977 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 4)
    - International Broadcast Institute, 1966 - 1974 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 5)
    - International Business Machines (IBM), 1970 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 6)
    - International Paper Company, 1970 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 7)
    - International Press Institute, 1967 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 8)
    - Invitations – accepted, 1966 - 1967 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 9)
    - Invitations – declined, 1966 - 1967 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 10-11)
    - Invitations – miscellaneous, 1967 - 1976 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 12-13)
    - J, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 14)
    - John and Mary R. Markel Foundation, 1970 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 15)
    - Johns Hopkins University, 1968 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 16)
    - K, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 17)
    - Kennedy, Roger G., 1971 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 18)
    - Kheel, Theodore W., 1967 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 19)
    - King Broadcasting Company, 1966 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 20)
    - Knopf, Alfred A., 1966 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 21)
    - Krosney, Herbert, 1969 - 1970 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 22)
    - Kubasik, Ben, 1966 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 23)
    - L, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 24)
    - Laskin, Paul L., 1967 - 1971 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 25)
    - Levin, Harvey J., 1970 - 1971 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 26)
    - Lippmann, Walter, 1966 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 27)
    - Litton, Glenn, 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 28)
    - London Weekend Television, 1969 - 1970 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 29)
    - Los Angeles Times, 1979 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 30)
    - Lowry, W. McNiel, 1966-1974 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 31)
    - Lurie, Ranan R., 1971 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 32)
    - Mac, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 33)
    - McGee, Frank, 1968 - 1970 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 34)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1967 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 35)
    - McNamara, Robert, 1966 - 1971 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 36)
    - MacNeil, Robert, 1969 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 37)
    - M, miscellaneous, 1966 - 1980 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 38)
    - Magat, Richard, 1967 - 1979 (Box 5 (33851), Folder 39)
    - Manning, Gordon, 1975 - 1980 (Box 6 (33858), Folder 1)
    - Markel, Lester, 1967 - 1977 (Box 6 (33858), Folder 2)